Among China's eight main cuisines
it's Sichuan fare that's the most popular
(Sichuan Cuisine)
widely served
and evocative of local culture
It is because the bulk of Sichuan's toothsome dishes
originate in local households
(Folk Gastronomy)
It's home cooking
(Home Cooking)
It's all around the country
(All around the country)
Among them all, Sichuan-style dishes
(Most Irresistible)
are the most popular
(Most Delectable)
Exotic flavors conjured from
ceaseless spicy experimentation
constitute the very soul of Sichuan cuisine
and its universal appeal
No fish is added to fish-flavored shredded pork
But the dish has a fishy flavor
(No Fish)
I think it contains fish
(Fish)
The flavor is not from fish
(A Matter of Philosophy)
It's a matter of philosophy
Tasting it is a moment of epicurean wonder
(Delicious)
The series presents Sichuan cuisine's
six most representative and influential dishes
Seemingly ordinary
each one has an intriguing backstory
(Sichuan Cuisine)
(Couple's Sliced Beef in Chili Sauce)
The popular Mapo Tofu was introduced to the world
by a housewife
Another dish known as the Couple's Sliced Beef in Chili Sauce
is credited to a poor couple
Most famous Sichuan dishes
derive from local home cooking
In Sichuan
many cooks
still explore new recipes
out of their love of food
Zhang Peng built a garden on his roof
where he grows vegetables
and also makes sausages
and preserved meat
Though he has made a name for himself on social media
as a connoisseur
he is first of all a developer of food
This garden
not only provides for his home cooking
and boutique catering
but also serves as
a food laboratory
On weekends
Zhang Peng's friends often
get together at his place
He loves to try his newly created dishes
One is
his version of
the couple's sliced beef in chili sauce
Preparation is required
This particular dish
is popular
and well-known
But it is by no means
common at family dinners
The reason is easy to explain
The ingredients
are not readily available
and the process
is complicated
It requires
beef scalp, tripe
tongue and heart
as well as sliced beef
Also, the innards
and various spices
require elaborate preparation
Seemingly simple
this dish is rather complicated indeed
Nowadays in Chengdu
you can find the dish in street markets and supermarkets
(Yuan Tingdong
Chengdu Folklore Scholar)
But simply mixing the ingredients and various spices together
won't produce the authentic taste
The original dish
has a secret condiment
locally called white sauce
(White Sauce)
The beef and innards are boiled in the white sauce first
After being cooled
they are sliced into thin pieces
Home-grown yellow celery is a good match for this dish
And tender ones are better
They are cut into small bits and laid on a plate
White celery or common celery won't do
They will spoil the flavor
(Zhang Peng
Folk Gourmet)
The key is to extract the aroma of the yellow celery
Without it, the dish will lose its flavor
Zhang Peng places the slices on the celery
pours the sauce over it
adds some soy sauce, MSG, sugar
salt and pepper, and mixes them together
The sauce should be added lavishly
It's the major flavor booster
It's made from the white sauce in which the ingredients are boiled
The sauce is the base
Without it, the dish will be dry and tasteless
It is indispensable
for making an excellent dish of couple's sliced beef in chili sauce
Finally, the chef adds chili oil
sprinkles some peanuts on it
(Couple's Sliced Beef in Chili Sauce)
and an exquisite dish with fine color and flavor
is done
Dinner is ready
Let's get started
"fu qi fei pian", the Chinese name of this dish
literally means husband and wife lung slices
But its ingredients do not include lungs
So why does it have this name?
(Chengdu, Sichuan Province)
More than 100 years ago
an area called Huang Cheng Ba in Chengdu
present-day Tianfu Square
was inhabited
by a Muslim community
In accordance with their religious customs
residents there mainly consume beef and lamb
Beef was their favorite
And the offal was discarded
Some local vendors
collected the leftovers
and invented a delicacy seasoned with chili oil and pepper
They sold this dish
by Sanqiao Bridge in Huang Cheng Ba
(Li Jieren (1891-1962)
Writer)
which is vividly described by a Sichuan writer Li Jieren
In his article written in August 1948, he mentioned that
(Chinese People's Clothing, Food, Housing and Transportation)
(After the beef scalp is cooked)
(it is cut into thin pieces which should be almost transparent)
(Then the sauce, pepper and spicy red oil are added and mixed well)
(The dish is brilliant red in color)
(and smooth, crunchy, spicy, and fragrant in taste)
(The inventor of this dish and the time of its creation remain unknown)
(It was only sold by Sanqiao Bridge in Chengdu)
(The vendor sat on one end of a short bench)
(with a clay pot placed on the other)
(The pot had a fence made of bamboo chopsticks)
(The sliced beef scalp and cheek were piled up in the pot)
(The spicy aroma attracted many passers-by)
Since this dish was cheap
buyers were mostly
from the lower class
But eventually
even noble people
couldn't resist the tempting fragrance
And they would look around as they pass the stand
If there was no acquaintance in sight
they will buy a small portion
quickly eat it
and be on their way
Therefore, this dish was also
referred to as "look around"
It was charged by the number of pieces
The dish's ingredients were cheap
so the price was low
and was popular among common citizens
It was often sold in clay pots
and was also called "potted beef"
(Yuan Tingdong
Chengdu Folklore Scholar)
The vendor prepared a large pot of the sliced beef
He'd stick a few chopsticks in the pot
and place the container on the roadside
Passers-by could grab a few pieces of beef with the chopsticks
choosing the biggest ones, the thickest ones
or the ones with the most sauce
They'd eat them and go on their way
Potted beef
is the most popular dish
enjoyed among common people
More than 100 years later
potted beef has changed from a product made from waste
to a unique food
Instead of being forgotten
it's being constantly developed nowadays
65 kilometers southwest of Chengdu
(Qionglai, Sichuan Province)
is Qionglai
There's a famous food called
milk noodles
(Chen Yuming
Inheritor of Milk Noodles)
The soup of the noodles is white with a yellow tinge
which looks like milk
So people called them "milk noodles"
In order to make authentic milk noodles
preparation should get started one day before
The key to the noodles is the soup
Boil pork bones
after washing them
and wait till the blood seeps out
When the water froths, the bones are taken out
cleaned and broken in the middle
They are then put in the cold water
and seasoned with ginger
pepper and salt
When the soup boils
the fire is turned down
and it is simmered until the meat comes off the bones
When the soup turns white, it's done
This generally takes overnight
The soup is made from pork backbones which are boiled for a long time
It takes over 10 hours each day to make this soup
Early in the morning
customers come to the noodle shop
The soup is freshly prepared
which is the best time to enjoy it
The cook pours the soup into a large bowl
The freshly made noodles are thin, smooth, and tender
Different sauces and condiments
are added according to the customer's order
The fragrant noodles, the mellow soup, and the tasty sauce
are mouth-watering
However, at this point
the breakfast is still incomplete
The other star on the breakfast table is bobo chicken
To the people of Qionglai
a meal that doesn't include hot and spicy food
is not satisfying
So they eat bobo chicken
made with chili pepper and other spices with their milk noodles
The tasty noodles and hot appetizing chicken suit their taste
(Chen Yuming
Inheritor of Milk Noodles)
When I was young, I was told that
bobo chicken was contained in an earthen jar
in which the chicken slices were laid on an upside-down bowl
Bobo means "earthen jar" in Chinese, and that is how the dish got its name
It used to be sold by peddlers who carried it on a long pole
We didn't have much money, so we seldom bought it
It cost 2 cents a slice
The origin of Qionglai bobo chicken is similar to
that of potted beef from Huang Cheng Ba, Chengdu
As living standards improved
the ingredients in the pot
kept changing
Nowadays, offal has been replaced by chicken
But local people, especially the elders
still call it by the old name
Also
bobo chicken is still sold by the piece
By afternoon
the shop has sold almost all its food
The noodle shop is closed
The staff begins preparing for the next day's bobo chicken
The cooks will simmer the soup in the evening
Day in and day out
these hardworking folks prepare food
to sustain the daily lives of the town's people
However the ingredients have changed in the pot
the dish has retained its form and taste
It's always spicy and delicious, inexpensive and good quality
The most famous type
is the couple's sliced beef in chili sauce
There's a story behind the origin of this dish
related to a couple
It's said that in the early 1930s
Guo Chaohua, a native of Zhongjiang County, Sichuan
joined the army and became a cook
(Wang Chujun
Son-in-law of Guo Chaohua)
I learned the story from my parents-in-law when they were both alive
My wife's father said he was an army cook
One day, during a march, he fell into a snowdrift and blacked out
Some local passers-by found him and saved him
Then he went back to Chengdu
and married a girl from Anyue named Zhang Tianzheng
Guo Chaohua and Zhang Tianzheng were an ordinary couple
Yet they managed to invent a well-known dish in Sichuan cuisine
This feat was related to their living conditions at that time
The newly married couple had no means of earning a living
When they saw the leftovers of a slaughterhouse
they collected them to make a dish, and then for sale
Starting in 1936
residents in Huang Cheng Ba
would often see a couple with a basket
peddling their food in every season and in all weather
(Depiction of Culinary Customs in Old Chengdu)
They were Guo Chaohua and Zhang Tianzheng
Taking notice of discarded beef hearts, tongues, and scalps
outside the meat shops
and inspired by the potted beef sold at Sanqiao Bridge
they had the idea to make a new dish with this offal
The couple experimented with the braising and seasoning process
They gradually developed a dish that was unique, tasty, and cheap
And it became popular
Because it was made from discarded beef offal and leftovers
consumers often refer to the dish as "fei" slices
meaning discarded slices
(Yuan Tingdong
Chengdu Folklore Scholar)
"Husband and wife lung slices" is the literal translation of the name
but actually it is not made of the lung of a cow
rather the leftovers, such as the scalp, liver, and stomach
The word "lung" is a homonym of "discarded" in Chinese
The couple's major customers were students and laborers
With 1 cent, they could have 2 to 3 pieces
The dish was tasty, and their customers liked the young couple
Some youngsters played a joke on them
by sticking a note on Guo Chaohua's back
which read "couple's discarded slices"
Later a local scholar changed the word "discarded" into its homonym "lung"
because the former had a negative connotation
In fact, it contains no lung pieces
This is how the word "discarded" was replaced with "lung"
The renaming of the dish
opened a new era for the couple
and their life greatly changed
In 1949, Chengdu was liberated
and the couple found a place to set up shop and sell their dish
In 1956, the Chengdu Catering Company
purchased all the famous local private food businesses, including theirs
The couple were both employed by the company
They continued to work there till they retired
In 1956, the couple's shop was purchased
and was nationalized in 1958
They were transformed from vendors to workers at a state-owned company
taking charge of the cooking procedure
The Chengdu Couple's Sliced Beef Shop
has inherited the traditional method of making this dish
and continues to modify and improve it
Wang Qinrui, the chief executive cook of the shop
is the current inheritor of the dish
(Wang Qinrui, Inheritor
Couple's Sliced Beef in Chili Sauce)
I'm the third-generation inheritor
My master learned directly
from Guo Chaohua and Zhang Tianzheng, the founders
Now the ingredients and condiments for the dish are fixed
which include beef scalp, heart
tongue, stomach, and beef itself
No lungs or other things are included
They are cleaned and boiled with over 20 spices
The formula is kept highly confidential
The staff's slicing skills are impressive
When they are cut, the slices should be as wide as a cow's hoof
and as thin as a cicada's wing
If you lay a slice on a book, you can clearly see the words on the page
The thinner it is, the stronger the flavor and the better the taste
The dish is cooked with various condiments
as well as small bits of celery and peanuts
along with the original sauce and soup
There are no chemical flavor boosters
Its supreme taste relies on the magical combination
of different spices, chili oil, and pepper powder
It's the love of husband and wife
that gave birth to this renowned dish
Zhang Tianzheng retired at the age of 55
and later she was reemployed to become a technical advisor
She kept that position until 1991 when she was 71 years old
In 1994, in Chengdu, a shop named Guo Couple's Discarded Slices
had its grand opening
This puzzled residents
who have long been accustomed to the name
"lung slices"
The owner of this store is Guo Ruiqiu
the eldest daughter of Guo Chaohua and Zhang Tianzheng
She chose the word "discarded"
to pay tribute to the old brand name
when her parents first created this dish
When she was a teenager
her parents taught her how to cook the dish
including selecting ingredients, slicing them
boiling the soup, making red chili oil
and the secret proportions of different condiments
She thus mastered the most authentic recipe for this dish
In 1994, Guo Chaohua passed away
In 2002, Zhang Tianzheng passed away
The creators of this legendary dish
finished their journey in the world of food
leaving behind a peerless delicacy
Chengdu media honored Zhang Tianzheng
as the longest-lived among all the founders of classic food brands
Her death marked the end of a legendary era of folk food
Food is born out of love
And the creation process of the couple's sliced beef in chili sauce
stands as solid proof of this
One article about it says
"The dish is not made of lungs
but its taste is multi-layered
hot, spicy, fresh, and fragrant."
The name of the dish is also auspicious for marital harmony and happy life